Finding Aid for Dwight L. Dumond papers, 1928-1970
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dwight L. Dumond papers 1928-1970
Dumond, Dwight Lowell, 1895-
2 linear feet
85152 Aa 2
Professor of history at the University of Michigan. Correspondence and other papers concerning his research and writings on the anti-slavery movement in America.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Dwight L. Dumond (donor no. 3695 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Dwight L. Dumond was born August 27, 1895, in Kingston, Ohio. He received a bachelor of arts degree at Baldwin-Wallace University in 1920, a master of arts degree at Washington University in 1928, and a Ph.D. degree in 1929 at Michigan. After teaching for a year at Ohio Wesleyan University, Dumond joined the University of Michigan faculty in 1930. He remained at Michigan until his retirement in 1965. Dumond was best known for his authoritative works on the history of slavery. The titles of some of his work were Antislavery Origins of the Civil War in the United States (1939) and Antislavery: The Crusade for Freedom in America (1961). Dumond was granted the University's Distinguished Faculty Achievement Award in 1963. He died May 30, 1976.
The Dumond collection contains professional correspondence, including letters received, ca. 1961-1970, reflecting prevailing attitudes towards race relations and the historiography of the American Civil War. There are also research materials, notebooks containing lecture notes and drafts of writings, reviews of his books, an audio-tape of a talk he gave, and a scattering of photographs.
Subjects:
Civil rights--United States.; Historians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; University of Michigan. Dept. of History.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; African Americans.; Antislavery movements--United States.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of History.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical / Personal
  - Personal material (Box 1)
  - Awards and honors (Box 1)
  - Photocopies of letters received upon occasion of retirement, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Personal clippings (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1928-1936 (Box 1)
  - 1937-1940 (Box 1)
  - 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - 1943-1950 (Box 1)
  - 1951-1955 (Box 1)
  - 1956 (Box 1)
  - 1957 (Box 1)
  - 1958 (Box 1)
  - 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  - 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - 1961-1963 concerning book Anti-Slavery, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (include much "hate" mail)
  - January-March 1963 (Box 1)
  - April-December 1963 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1964 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1964 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1964 (Box 1)
  - 1965 (Box 1)
  - 1966 (Box 1)
  - 1967 (Box 1)
  - 1968 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1969 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970 (Box 1)
- Other materials
  - Programs and notices of speeches, lectures, and awards (Box 1)
  - Research material
    - School segregation (Box 1)
    - Brown vs. Board of Education... 1954 (Box 1)
    - Biographical information on anti-slavery leaders (Box 1)
  - Articles and other writings
    - Book reviews (Box 1)
    - Educational consultation reports (Box 1)
    - Published articles, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Ledger containing personal financial information (Box 2)
  - Notebooks containing lecture notes and drafts of writings, 8 volumes (Box 2)
  - Reviews of Dumond's book (Box 2)
  - Books by or containing articles by Dwight Lowell Dumond (Box 2)
  - Audio-tape of talk, July 1965, WNMR Northern Dimensions, 1 sound cassette (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
    ( includes portraits; photographs of DLD receiving award, giving a speech, and in his office with students; and photographs of display relating to his book on anti-slaver)